校对:  Uezaki，Azonker，-俄刻阿诺斯
翻译，时间轴，压制: Bolshevik0
下划线原文为油管自动字幕有问题且我没听清的部分
In my time of being an anime fan
在我成为动画粉丝的这段时间里
I've seen this medium grow and evolved beyond my wildest dream.
这种媒介的成长与演变远超我的期待
注: 本期anime指的是日本动画，简称动画，多数情况下，anime并非指欧美本土动画
顺便心疼法国动画一秒
Being an anime fan in 2018 is not only accepted
在8102年 2018年成为一个动画粉不仅能被公众接受
but it is exciting with countless shows to choose from, communities to get involved with
而且还很刺激 有无数的动画可以选择观看 有无数的社区可以参与
and an industry that is getting the growth we always thought it deserved.
还有一个我们觉得会一直蒸蒸日上的业界
The landscape is becoming something unrecognizable from when I first entered it.
形势与我刚入坑的时候产生了极大的变化
And I am undoubtedly happy about that.
毋庸置疑 我对此感到很高兴
But there have been some things I have been nagging me for the longest time about this modern landscape.
但是一提到现在的动画 有些东西总在困扰着我
A shadow that's been looming over that I can't help but notice.
我察觉到了一片阴影的缓慢出现
And it's not something straightforward and obvious to point out.
想指明它并不容易
So I'm not really sure where I should begin.
所以我也不知道该从何讲起
Just a humble bounty hunter man.
不过是个低调的赏金猎人
So how about I start right here with me
不如在这里和我一起开始
which sorry to break the immersion of having nice aesthetic anime clips as opposed to my face
啊真是不好意思打扰了各位享受艺术动画剪辑中的美好沉浸感而要直面我的脸
吐槽: Vegas瞩目 (诚心默念Vegas好)
but to probably get my point across,
为了较好地传达我的观点
I wanted to tell you a story.
我想讲个故事
It's my story.
我的故事
And it starts right there.
从这里开始的我的故事
In that shed.
就在那个棚屋里
These are VHS tapes recordings of Pokemon
这些是宝可梦 的VHS录像带
back when they first aired on ITV .
可以追溯到它在ITV 刚上映的那段时间
And it is the birth of my anime fandom.
这也是我入坑动画的开端
I, like many others, first got their exposure to anime through Pokemon
我和很多其他人一样 通过宝可梦 第一次接触到了动画
which wasn't so weird considering how much of a worldwide sensation it was.
考虑到宝可梦 在世界上传播的广泛性 这并不奇怪
What was weird was that
奇怪的则是
注: 这里指的应该是Gigguk小时候在周围的小伙伴之中 只有他在宝可梦 热潮过后还在看
I was the only one still watching it way after the craze had died out.
我是唯一一个在热潮过后还在看它的人
And afterwards I would obsessively try to look for every other show
之后我痴迷于寻找
that had the same similar art style.
每一个和宝可梦 有着类似风格的动画
Because I was the only one who liked this kind of show.
因为我是唯一一个喜欢动画的人
And that's continued to my teenage years
这在我青少年时期得以延续
where I would discover what anime was thanks to the Internet.
多谢互联网的存在 那时我真正弄清楚了日本动画
Now I knew nobody who liked anime
现在我知道那时基本没人喜欢动画
and even those of us on the Internet were in really small communities.
就算是网上的动画粉丝团体也只是处在一个极小的一部分
And this would transition to my first DVD collection
直到我买第一套DVD合集的时候发生了转变
which actually consists mostly of bootlegs
其实包含了许多盗版碟
before I realized that eBay was not a licensed seller of anime.
那时我还不知道eBay 没有卖动画类产品的授权
Now a lot of these first buyers came from this standardized list of shows
现在许多买碟新人都来自这个标准化动画清单
that would be constantly recommended by these small communities you'd find online.
而这些清单往往是被那些网上的小社区所推荐的
Now that weren't a lot of us but as a newbie,
当然这不是我们中的大多数 但是作为一个新人
these were the shows you had to watch.
这些动画你必须要看
Because these were the classics.
因为这些动画是经典
Back in the day, anime fans had this unwritten rite of passage
那时候 动画粉丝有个不成文的认证仪式
you'd have to go through before you could pass yourself off as a Real Anime Fan.
你必须得证明你是真动画粉
Cowboy Bebop
星际牛仔
Akira
阿基拉
Fullmetal Alchemist
钢之炼金术师
Black……
Black Bible
吐槽: 这是车，别乱搜
And when you wanted to take on the final boss,
而当你要对付最终Boss的时候
you take a deep breath,
你深呼吸一下
put on your big boy pants
穿上你那宽松的男孩短裤
and dive into the cluster fuck that was Evangelion discussions.
然后逃入人群中 这就是我们所说的EVA
Well I'm glad a lot of this mentality of real anime fans is past now
当然我很高兴这些辣鸡死宅心态现在已经消失了
with a lot of the elitism it bred.
尽管这影响了不少大佬
These were the shows everyone watch
这些确实是那些年每个人都看过的动画
because they were the shows that were talked about no matter what year you got into anime.
在以前 不管你是哪年入坑 你都会讨论这些动画
And that's because of what the landscape was like back then as a fan.
这是因为在那个时候 整个动画粉丝圈的形势 只是作为粉丝而已
Being a fan then meant that you were a part of this niche community
成为粉丝意味着你成为了这个小众社区的一员
where all our common grounds was that we'd liked anime.
而那时我们聚集到一起共同的理由不过是我们喜欢动画
Cuz finding another person who did was a rare enough thing back then.
那时确实很难找到另一个同好
And these shows were typically some of the best and known stuff we had
一般而言这些动画都是我们那时所知的最好最知名的作品
in the limited availability we were given.
要么其他更好的动画也是因为供应限制而无法看到
We were limited by what licensing companies would choose to bring over
我们受限于那些代理公司的选择引进的动画
or what fans subbers would choose to sub.
或者是字幕组选择制作字幕的那些动画
Everything certainly wasn't readily available or instantly transferred over from Japan.
并不是所有的日本动画能马上从日本传过来
Legal or otherwise.
无论合法与否
And because of this our approach to watching anime was different.
因此我们看动画的方法因人而异
Choice was limited so people would invest time into finding a great anime for them.
选择是有限的 因此人们需要花费时间来为自己找好动画
Anime reviews held way more power than they do now
动画评论者比现在所拥有的影响力大得多
because there was a higher level of commitment when choosing to watch a show.
因为以前看动画需要更多的付出
You didn't want to waste money on a show you didn't like
你不想在你不喜欢看的动画上花钱
and even having torrents was less accessible than the one-click instant streaming accessibility of today.
就算是通过种子下载也没有现在这种一键立刻播放的视频流服务方便
So he meant way more when he found a good show.
所以找好动画的意义比现在大得多
The shows were what defines the anime fandom
这些好动画定义了动画粉丝文化
along with the weirdness and eccentricities we had.
与此同时还有那些古怪的行为
Being an anime fan felt like you were in this weird club separate from other communities.
成为一个动画粉丝就像是你在一个与世隔绝的团体之内
Something you couldn't find anywhere else.
有些东西你在别的地方是找不到的
In fact one of the biggest things that stops the fandom from growing
事实上 阻止这个粉丝团体继续扩张的一大原因
was just how exclusive it felt.
就是它有多么独特
Yes anime fans were weird but that's the commonality we shared as a community.
没错 动画粉丝是有些奇怪 但这是我们作为一个团体所共有的特性
And while certainly not everything was positive,
当然不是所有的东西都是正面的
things were definitely simpler.
总体上来讲都比现在要更纯粹
So if that's the way things were like,
以前是这样
what's changed today.
那现在又如何呢
Today anime has changed a lot.
现在的动画确实有很大改变
Well anime shows themselves have arguably remained the same for the most part.
当然 动画大多数部分仍饱受争议地保持着原来的样子
But the landscape itself is undoubtedly different.
但是整个形势却毋庸置疑地发生了变化
Let's start with the biggest change that killed off the idea of the classics.
我们从经典 理念的消亡这个最大的改变开始讲起
Seasonal anime.
季度番
Seasonal anime or should I say current anime
季度番或者说是现在在播的番
has taken over the viewing habits of the modern anime fandom
控制了现代动画粉丝圈的观看习惯
even if you're not following weekly.
就算你不是每周都追着看
It's about the shows that have aired in the last few months
包括那些过去几个月内播出的动画
and the cycle of what is and isn't current now
可能这个播出周期并不涵盖现在
is like three fucking days after a show ends.
可能是完结后的三天这样
Being part of the community
成为社区的一员
these are the shows you need to keep up with to be a part of the conversation.
看完这些动画你才能跟得上话题
It's an ongoing cycle that just becomes our viewing habits.
这个不断发展的周期成为了我们的观看习惯
The idea of the standardized list of classic anime,
标准化经典番剧观看清单的主意
everyone watches to keep up with the current consensus of the fandom is dead.
那些让大家看完之后达成共识的粉丝圈已经死了
Before I felt like the entire timeline of anime was always up for grabs,
在我感觉整个动画的时间表都是用来吸引眼球之前
for newbies you had your rough starting point.
对于新人来讲 你的入门并不会那么顺利
Boom x 4
Go do your homework.
回去做作业去
Also don't forget your history lesson here.
也别忘了这些历史课
Now it's about what's hot.
现在来讲讲什么比较流行
What's not.
什么不流行
Let's give everything a fucking try.
我来举个例
What's an anime that seems like he could go somewhere after three episodes.
三集定律
What? It turns out the show sucked.
什么 是个烂番
Oh you fucking idiots.
吔屎啦你
Why would you waste your time like that.
你怎么可以花时间看烂番
Ok, this time it definitely won't happened to me.
当然 这次这些东西绝不会在我身上发生
As creatures of habit we are stuck in this endless cycle.
作为习惯的生物 我们会卡在这个无尽的循环中
And as constitutive as it sounds
基本上来讲
the important thing isn't about finding those killer shows you haven't seen yet
重要的不是找那些没看过的好看的动画来看
and would really appreciate.
并对此真心感谢
Our big motivator to watch shows now
现在我们看番的最大动机
is becoming part of a conversation.
是参与到话题中来
Having our water cooler discussions,
参与我们冷静的讨论
we can have multiple shows we are simply content with as long as we get to discuss it with someone.
只要是那些我们能和别人讨论的动画 就能让人满意
And the thing is mentality in part started from something
而这种糟糕的心态
that initially looked like a massive upside
发展自某种一开始看起来是个蛮积极的东西
and that is that there is so much fucking anime coming out right now.
但也就仅此而已了 现在有太多辣鸡动画
And it only keeps increasing.
还在不断增加
Ten years ago we celebrated the innovation of streaming companies.
十年前我们在庆祝视频流公司的诞生
They gave us official anime simulcast with the same day release of Japan.
它们给我们带来了和日本官方相同的连载动画发布时间
Five years ago you could just about keep up with all the shows worth watching
五年前你能恰好跟上所有值得观看的动画
while occasionally discovering something new.
与此同时偶尔发现一些新系列
Today you better be jacked into the Matrix directly absorbing the anime into your 300 IQ brain
今天你最好直接脑后插管通过你那智商300的大脑连接母体 并吸收动画
because no sane fan can keep up with everything coming out.
因为没有那个疯狂的粉丝可以跟上所有发布出来的东西
I can't even keep up with all the anime coming out now
我都不能跟上所有现在发布出来的动画
and it's my fucking job to watch anime.
尽管我的工作是看动画
You might as well rename your plan to watch this.
你也许会变更你的观看计划来观看这些
你们这群死宅 你知道你永远也看不完的
Anime is such a wide world with so much variety in history
日本动画历史上涉及的种类如此之广泛
filled with amazing shows.
充满了神作
But when we're absolutely overwhelmed for the choice,
但是当我们选择太多的时候
what do we watch?
我们该看什么
We watch what's right in front of us.
我们看正前方出现的
We watch what we heard being discussed by our friends.
我们看朋友们讨论的
You log in to the front page of my streaming platforms,
你登进视频流播放平台的首页
legal or otherwise and you're hit in the face with simulcast,
不管合法与否 你都会看到一堆连载中的动画
new seasonal episodes,
季度新番
currently airing shows.
现在正播出的动画
If you're a casual viewer searching for something new
如果你只是想随便找点动画来看
or even if you just want a new show
亦或是想找个新动画来看
but don't know what you're in the mood for,
但是不知道自己喜欢哪种类型的
where are you even supposed to start?
你该从何开始
Okay did I miss anything from last season.
好的 让我看看上个季度我错过了什么
Let me see the list.
让我看一下清单
Okay, what about two seasons, last year.
好的 再多看两个季度 或者是去年的
Two years.
两年前的
Okay I think I have enough now to last me through two nuclear winters.
好的 光看这些我甚至可以熬过两个核冬天了
应该很好
Everything is available.
动画都能看到
Everything is abundant.
种类都很丰富
But because of this, we're ironically more limited than we used to be.
但也因此 讽刺地是 我们比过去受到的限制更多
But really as much as some people would take this as,
但是会有些人这么认为
Hey, look at this idiot complaining about too much anime.
嘿 这有个喷子居然在喷动画太多
hahahaha.
哈哈哈哈.
What I wanted to get out is that this is just a product of what the medium has become
这是动画这个媒介变化后的产物
and how our attitude towards media has changed in general.
而大体上 我们看媒体的方式也发生了改变
So let me ask you this.
所以如果我问你
What makes anime special
在这个大众消费丰富的现代媒体形势中
in this modern media landscape of mass consumption abundance of choice
是什么让日本动画独树一帜
and mainstream nerd culture.
当然也包括主流nerd文化
As time goes on the answer becomes increasingly nothing.
随着时间的推移 这个回答逐渐变得没有意义
I think the sense Minh truly hit me
我认为快进党的这个说法真的冲击到我了
when I started hearing from several different people
当我听说好几个人
how they would watch anime at 1.25 or 1.5 speed
都是1.25倍速或者1.5倍速看动画的时候
if they just wanted to get through a show.
当他们只是想看完动画的时候
And hearing that just blew my fuckin mind.
听到这个真的让我震惊
The fact that we the viewer could treat our entertainment as a commodity
事实上观众可以把娱乐当作一种快消品
that we try to consume and process as fast as we can.
就是一种消费得越快越好的东西
That's why I'm talking to you son of a bitch.
我在说你呢
Stop watching this video 1.5 speed.
别用1.5倍速看这个视频了
I'm trying to make a point.
我正在发表看法
But the reality is anime is just another form of media
不过事实上动画也就是一种传播媒介而已
that we consume in this modern age of digital consumption and we consume a lot.
只是我们在这个现代数字消费时代消费的很多东西中的一种
Anime doesn't only have to compete with other anime.
动画不只是和别的动画竞争
It has to compete with games, movies, YouTube,
它也需要和游戏 电影 油管
some fucking idiot starting drama on Twitter again.
甚至一些推特上的戏精
We are living in an age where time is limited and choice is abundant.
我们生活在一个时间有限但选择过于丰富的年代
Our most limiting resource when it comes to our entertainment now is no longer our money.
现在在娱乐上面 受限的资源并不是我们的钱
It's our time.
而是我们的时间
It's our attention.
是我们的注意力
And media outlets have become very very good at capitalizing on it.
而媒体公司非常擅长在这个上面压榨价值
There's no longer that stop signal you used to have.
不再有以前那样的停止符号了
Netflix tells you you don't even need to care about the end credits.
Netflix 甚至告诉你 你不需要关注片尾制作名单
The next recommended YouTube video is auto-played by default.
下一个油管推荐视频甚至是默认自动播放
Your timeline is a bottomless pit you can scroll endlessly down.
你的时间线就是个无底洞 你可以无尽地往下滚动
And as a side effect,
而副作用是
our attention span have become incrementally shorter.
我们关注一件事的时间变得越来越短
How many of you have sometimes looked at 20-minute anime episode of thought,
你们有多少人看20分钟动画的时候会想
Wow 20 minutes.
哇 20分钟呢
That's a pretty big commitment.
这是个很大的投入
Maybe I'll watch it after this short 6-minute YouTube video.
也许我应该先看这个6分钟的油管短视频
Oh fuck.
我去
Even with shows in a modern day we find amazing.
甚至是现在我们觉得很好看的动画
It feels like there's very little chance it'll even be thought about five, three, even one year later.
感觉5年后 3年后 甚至1年后都不太可能想得起来
Because it just gets swallowed up
因为它被新事物淹没了
as being another show in the endless pit of media we consume.
成为有一个我们消费过然后丢在无底洞里的动画
Resume Viewing.x6
继续观看x6
The reality is anime isn't as distinct as it used to be in the grand scheme of things.
事实上动画并没有以前那么独树一帜
As it has become a more widely accepted medium of entertainment
正如它变成了一种广为人知的娱乐媒介
that exclusivity of the anime fandom is also disappearing
动画粉丝圈的独特性也在消失
for the better in my opinion.
当然也不坏
But going with it is the uniqueness of being an anime fan.
但是一同消失的也包括成为动画粉丝的独特性
In the same way no one really says they're just a straight up gaming fan.
就像是没有谁会直接说他是一个游戏粉丝一样
Saying you're an anime fan nowadays feels less like you're a part of a niche tight community.
现在说自己是个动画粉丝 并不会像以前那样感觉自己处在一个关系密切的小众社区
But more like you're a part of a general movement.
但是感觉更像是处在一个大众活动当中
Cuz it could mean a load of different things.
因为这意味着许多不同的东西
Do you only watch Shounen, Mecha, Idols?
你只看少年 机甲 偶像 类动画吗
Are you a casual viewer, cosplayer, artist, animator, data entry clerk for your watch list?
你做出这个动画观看列表 是因为你是漫不经心的观众 角色扮演 艺术家 动画制作者还是数据录入员
Anime fan means a whole different thing than he used to
动画粉丝这个词和以前大不一样了
and in an age where we could have something in common
以前我们能有一些共同点
with people like Michael B. Jordan and John Boyega and Kim fucking Kardashian.
哪怕是Michael B. Jordan和John Boyega还有KimKardashian
The biggest difference about being an anime fan today is this.
现在的动画粉丝的巨大不同就在于此
It's not just about the anime shows anymore.
不仅仅是关于动画作品本身
It's about the anime culture.
还关于动画文化
The weirdness and eccentricities have become normalized and accepted.
稀奇古怪的东西被正常化并被接受了
The anime aesthetic is becoming widely spread.
动画的艺术性被广泛地传播了
It's about that social aspect that was never as prevalent before.
在社会上 动画从未有现在这样如此流行
It's about being part of the conversation and that's fine.
现在俨然成为了讨论的一部分
But I think because of this we need to recognize that
正因如此 我们需要承认
our approach to the medium shouldn't be the same as it used to be.
现在我们观看媒体的方式和过去不一样了
Because I think for a lot of us it still is.
就算是对于我们动画粉丝而言也是这样
Anime is no longer that same niche little community.
日本动画不再是以前那个小众社区了
It's no longer any guarantee that
不能保证
2 people who call themselves anime fans will have the same kind of common ground they used to.
两个动画粉丝之间就像以前一样还有相同的兴趣爱好
Because we are becoming too big to simply segregate into one group
因为动画粉丝团体变得太过庞大 无法再按以前那样分成一个类别
and I think it's also time we drop the notion
现在是总结的时候了
that we should try to keep up with everything anime has to offer.
我们应该尽力跟上动画所提供的一切
It used to be that as an anime fan you could be aware of every new show.
过去一个动画粉丝可以知晓每个新推出的动画
Everything worth talking about.
每件事都值得讨论
Everything that the community was doing.
正如整个社区所做的事一样
But I think we've reached the breaking point
但是我认为现在到达了一个转折点
where it's reasonable to feel pressure to keep up.
有足够的理由不再跟上动画的脚步
In the same way that no one feels pressure to watch every movie that comes out worldwide.
同理 没有谁应该为不能看到所有推出的电影而感到压力
Nor do people feel pressured to keep up with every game that comes out on Steam.
或者是不能玩到所有Steam 上推出的游戏
A lot of the discussion around piracy recently have been around the inconvenience of
盗版领域人们最近总在讨论
so many different shows being distributed on different platforms.
这么多动画在不同的平台发布带来的不方便
But with too many shows to choose from the starts becoming less of an issue.
但是因为可选择的动画太多了 这反而不再是大问题了
What's likely to happen is that the casual consumer will end up just filing shows
有可能发生的是 观众们只是把他们认为有趣的动画归档起来
that interest them on their platform or preference like most people do with their entertainment.
就像人们对待他们的娱乐活动一样
It won't become about keeping up with the community and the fandom.
日本动画不再是和社区或者粉丝圈保持一致步调
It becomes about what's marketed the most and what's most visible.
而是关于哪些东西是卖得最好的 是最引人注目的
It becomes about who can best generate hype for their products.
是关于那些最会炒作的
It becomes as you guessed it like every other industry.
就像任何其他行业一样
Because that's exactly what's happened.
正如现在所发生的一样
The industry in the West is now dominated by massive corporations.
西方世界的行业现在被大集团所把控
or smaller anime focus brands that are now owned by massive corporations.
或者是一些小动画品牌被大集团控制
It's no longer just that same fan-run industry used to be
不再是以前那个粉丝驱动的行业了
and with the money being invested into it,
随着金钱的投入
the companies have to realize that the audiences are starting to treat them
公司企业会意识到
with the same corporate standards and expectations that they do for other industries.
观众会像其他行业那样用相同的标准和期待来对待他们
What I want to end on is just hammering down
我想像这样一锤定音
that this isn't meant to be a complaint about how things have gotten worse or that the old days were better.
就是这个视频并不是为了抱怨现在变得更差而以前更好
I love anime today.
我现在还喜欢着动画
I love what it has become.
我也喜欢它变化后的样子
And the friends and opportunities I've gotten because of it.
同样也喜欢因为动画而结识的朋友和机遇
But as exactly because of this then I feel the medium is reaching a crossroads.
正因如此我觉得这个行业正面临一个转折点
It might not be on the same level as things like gaming or Marvel movies just yet.
可能并不会达到游戏或者漫威 电影那样
But the medium I grew up loving has also grown up,
可是我成长时期喜欢的那个动画产业现在也长大了
and it's coming to the time where I have to change the way I see it,
现在到了那个我需要改变我的看法的时候了
when it was something small and niche and well, special.
动画行业不再是以前那样小而独特
Things aren't as simple as they used to be
也不会像以前那样简单
and we should keep this in mind as we transition into something bigger
我们需要知道的是我们这个团体变得比以前更加庞大
and anime finds a space in the modern entertainment landscape.
而动画在现代娱乐产业中找到了自己的一席之地
Anime has changed.
动画变了
The community has changed.
社区变了
The industry has changed.
行业变了
We've changed.
我们观众也变了
And I think the time has come that the way we treat it, has to change.
也到了我们必须改变对待它的方法的时候了
动画和主流到底有多近？
注: 原视频链接和赞助链接见简介